<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The right vvay: or A direction for obtaining good successe in a weighty enterprise. Set out in a sermon preached on the 12th of September, 1648. before the Lords on a day of humiliation for a blessing on a treaty between His Majesties and the Parliaments commissioners. / By W. Gouge.</title>
            <author>Gouge, William, 1578-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E463_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202327</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862655</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862655</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85486)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 74:E463[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The right vvay: or A direction for obtaining good successe in a weighty enterprise. Set out in a sermon preached on the 12th of September, 1648. before the Lords on a day of humiliation for a blessing on a treaty between His Majesties and the Parliaments commissioners. / By W. Gouge.</title>
                  <author>Gouge, William, 1578-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Miller for Ioshua Kirton at the signe of the Spread-Eagle in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLVIII. [1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached before the Right honourable House of Peers. Sept. 12. 1648.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114824:1"/>
            <p>The Right Way:
OR
A DIRECTION
FOR
Obtaining good Succeſſe in a
weighty Enterpriſe.
<hi>Set out in</hi>
A SERMON PREACHED
on the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> 1648.
BEFORE THE
LORDS
On a day of Humiliation for a Bleſſing on a
TREATY between His MAJESTIES and
the PARLIAMENTS Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> W. Gouge.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JER. 4. 21.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</p> 
               <bibl>Gal. 5. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> Orat. 14. § 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Quid eſt Pax? De incertis non judicat: incognita non confirmat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p> 
               <bibl>Aug.
<hi>Enar. in Pſal.</hi> 147.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Miller</hi> for <hi>Ioſhua Kirton</hi> at the Signe of the
Spread-Eagle in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, M. DC. XL VIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114824:2"/>
            <head>TO THE
RIGHT HONOURABLE HOUSE
OF
PEERS
Aſſembled in
PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE</hi> Occaſion <hi>of your appointing
this</hi> Sermon <hi>to be preached,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this work is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon following <hi>pag.</hi> 32, 34.</note> 
               <hi>was a</hi>
Matter <hi>of no ſmall</hi> moment. <hi>It is
thus expreſſed in Your own Order:</hi>
A day appointed to be obſerved
by both Houſes of PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT,
for publike Humiliation,
and to ſeek God earneſtly for a Bleſſing upon the
Treaty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>End</hi> of this <hi>Treaty,</hi> is to cloſe up and heal the
breaches of this Land.</p>
            <p>A pious End!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So great is the</hi> Breach, <hi>as it giveth great and just
cauſe of deep</hi> Humiliation, <hi>I may in this caſe apply
<pb facs="tcp:114824:3"/>
the</hi> Prophets lamentation <hi>for</hi> Jeruſalem (<hi>Lament.</hi> 2.
13.) <hi>unto</hi> England. What thing ſhall I take to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
for thee? What thing ſhall I liken to thee,
<hi>O England?</hi> For thy Breach is great, like the
Sea.</p>
            <p>Not without cauſe therefore have You ſet apart this day for
publike Humiliation.<note place="margin">The grounds of this difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are ſet down, p. 34, 35 <hi>Virg.</hi> AEn. lib. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To make up this <hi>Breach</hi> is a <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hic labor, hoc opus eſt—</p>
            <p>It is beyond the wit and power of man to do it.</p>
            <p>Good reaſon therefore there was to appoint the day of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milation</hi>
to be a day alſo <hi>to ſeek God earneſtly for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
upon the Treaty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>breach</hi> be not ſtopped by a <hi>Treaty,</hi> by what may it
be ſtopped?</p>
            <p>Can it be hoped that it ſhould be done by ſword? The Law
is dumb while the Sword is drawn.<note place="margin">Silent leges in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter arma. <hi>Cic</hi> pre <hi>Milon.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Will Conquerours yeeld to an Accommodation? Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
the ſtaff in their own hands, Will they not ſtand upon their
own terms?</p>
            <p>By force men may for a time be kept in awe.<note place="margin">Malus eſt cuſt<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s diuturnitatis, metus. Cic. Offic l. 2.</note> But that
AWE is no good keeper of a laſting peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> It will be Your Wiſdome and
Glory,<note place="margin">Hominis gratia Numinis reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia non eſt violenda.</note> to help on this <hi>Treaty, Uſque ad aras:</hi> ſo farre
as may ſtand with piety and verity: with ſafety and ſecurity
of Church and State.</p>
            <p>That under GOD, Ye may be happy instruments here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
two things are requiſite, both on <hi>Your</hi> own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe
and alſo on the behalfe of all the <hi>People</hi> of this
<hi>Land,</hi> whom a good iſsue of the <hi>Treaty</hi> doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:114824:3"/>
1. <hi>Sound</hi> Repentance.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Hearty</hi> Praier.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our ſinnes, our ſinnes have made the breach. Our</hi>
Repentance <hi>muſt make to the repairing of the breach.</hi> The
people repented them for Benjamin, becauſe the
LORD had made a breach in the tribes of Iſrael,
<hi>Judg.</hi> 21. 15.</p>
            <p>Their Cauſe was juſt,<note place="margin">De victoria ſibi non tantum gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulantur, quam de clade tribus Iſraeleticae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queruntur.</note> yet they <hi>repented</hi> when they ſaw
how great the <hi>breach</hi> was. They did not ſo much glorie
in their victory, as grieve for the deſtruction of a Tribe
in Iſrael.</p>
            <p>And is not the <hi>breach</hi> made among us a great <hi>breach?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wolph. <hi>Serm. 91. in</hi> Judg. 21.</note>
Surely it is <hi>great like the Sea. Who can heal thee,</hi> O
England?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quiſe opponit irae Dei ſaevien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. <hi>Hier.</hi> Com. in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58.</note> 
               <hi>and He only, who may most properly be called,</hi> The
repairer of the breach. <hi>To him therefore let us pray
and ſay,</hi> O GOD, thou haſt caſt us off: thou haſt ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
us:<note place="margin">Fruſtra opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius omnia mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liretur extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, niſi Creator intrinſecus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenter operare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> thou haſt been diſpleaſed: O turn thy ſelf to
us again. Thou haſt made the earth to tremble: Thou
haſt broken it. Heal the breaches thereof, for it ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</p>
            <p>All outward endeavours of workmen will be in vain, unleſs
the Creatour doe alſo inwardly work.<note place="margin">Noveritis vos plus proficere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationibus quam exhortationibus. <hi>Aug</hi> de Bon. vid. c. 18.</note> Know for certain, that
more may be done by praiers to GOD, then by perſwaſions
with men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi> It concerneth You moſt of all to take care
of this <hi>Matter:</hi> for the LORD hath made You, together
with the <hi>Honourable Houſe of Commons,</hi> Pillars to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
this State.</p>
            <p>Mention is made of two Pillars which <hi>Salomon</hi> made in
the Temple:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſunt propria nomina Alteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> derivatur <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> perſecit Inde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> rectum.</note> The one whereof he called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jachin:</hi> and the
other <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Boaz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:114824:4"/>
Thoſe two words are uſed as proper names. The former im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth,
<hi>ſtraitnes.</hi> The later, <hi>ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Pillars whereon Edifices doe rest be not as <hi>Jachin</hi> and
<hi>Boaz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alterum à <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> obfirmavit. Inde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> robur.</note> 
               <hi>ſtreight</hi> and <hi>ſtrong,</hi> they cannot be ſerviceable.
If they be not ſtreight, but crooked, the building reſting on
them, may ſway aſide. If they be not ſtrong, but weak, and
the burden reſting on them, heavy, they may fail, and the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
fall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>magnanimity</hi> will do much for quieting our
preſent diſtractions.</p>
            <p>The LORD pour upon you the ſpirit of <hi>Counſel</hi> and
<hi>Courage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lords, <hi>I am</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant<lb/>
and hearty Oratour<lb/>
William Gouge.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Blackfriers London</hi>
                  <date>19. Sept. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114824:4"/>
            <head>The Right Way:
OR
A DIRECTION
FOR
Obtaining good Succeſſe in a
weighty Enterpriſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>EZRA 8. 21.</bibl>
                  <p>Then I proclaimed a fast there, at the river Ahava, that
we might afflict our ſelves before our God, to ſeek of
him a right way for us, and for our little ones, and
for all our ſubſtance.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His text is taken out of the firſt of thoſe<note n="*" place="margin">Ezra, Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, Eſther.</note>
three Hiſtoricall books, which the holy
Ghoſt ſaw meet to be recorded for all ages,
concerning the ſtate of the Jewiſh Church,
after their return from their ſeventy years ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivity
under the <hi>Babylonians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Three Patriots came from the captivity to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They had three famous Patriots, who each of them
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114824:5"/>
one after another, came to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for ſome ſpeciall
good to the Church of God.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> to re-edifie the Temple:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zorobbabel</hi> extronit Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum. Civitas extruſta eſt ſub <hi>Neemia,</hi> Hier. <hi>l.</hi> 13. Comment. in <hi>Eſa.</hi>
               </note> which, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
the many impediments which he met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
at length he effected.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Ezra,</hi> to reform Religion: which notwithſtanding
the many corruptions he found there, he brought to
paſſe.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> to make up the wals of their City, for
their better ſafety and ſecurity: which notwithſtanding
the many oppoſitions made againſt him, he accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
            <p>That which is here ſpoken of in my Text, was done by
the ſecond of thoſe Patriots: who was a pious Prieſt, and
a prudent Governour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he came to</hi> Jeruſalem,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Context. Eſdras</hi> reſtituit legem. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Mir. S. S. l. 2. c. 33.</note> 
               <hi>to reform Religion, and
to ſettle the true worſhip of God, and a good govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in the Church, is evident by this teſtimony given
unto him,</hi> Ezra had prepared his heart, to ſeek the law of the
Lord, and to doe it, and to teach in Iſrael ſtatutes and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<hi>chap. 7. 10. So much is alſo evident by that charge
which</hi> Artaxerxes <hi>King of</hi> Perſia <hi>in his letters patents
thus gave unto him,</hi> Thou art ſent to enquire concerning Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah
and Jeruſalem, according to the law of thy God which is in
thine hand, and to carry the ſilver and gold which the king
and his councellers have freely offered unto the God of Iſrael;
&amp;c. <hi>chap.</hi> 7. 14, 15, 23.</p>
            <p>The end which he aimed at, being a very weighty and
worthy end, he prudently uſeth the beſt means, that he
could finde warranted in Gods Word, for good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
in his under aking thereabout. That means be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
here ſet down in my Text, I paſſe by all bie paſſages,
and directly come to my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114824:5"/>
               <hi>The Summe of it is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Summe of the Text.</note> A Direction for obtaining good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
in a weighty enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe that this generall Summe, doth ſufficiently
demonſtrate how ſeaſonable this Text is for our preſent
occaſion: which is to crave a bleſſing of God upon the
Treaty to be had betwixt his Majeſties and our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>The firſt particle in my Text,<note place="margin">The meaning of the words.</note> tranſlated <hi>then,</hi> is in the
Hebrew a copulative conjunction <hi>Vau, and.</hi> It knitteth
together the care that <hi>Ezra</hi> had in gathering together
ſuch perſons as were needfull for him, and might be
uſefull and helpfull unto him (<hi>verſe</hi> 18, 19, 20.)
and the means which by Gods Word was warranted
for procuring a bleſſing upon their endeavours.<note place="margin">Humane helps and divine bleſſing muſt go together.</note> Thus he
joyneth humane helps, and divine aſſiſtance together. He
doth <hi>this</hi> and <hi>that.</hi> To omit humane warranted helps, is
to tempt God; as the devil would have Chriſt done,
when he bid him caſt himſelf down from the pinacle of
the Temple, there being ordinary means whereby he
might ſafely deſcend, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 5, 6. To truſt to humane
helps without God is to neglect God, and to preſume:
as <hi>Aſa</hi> did, 2 <hi>Chron. 16. 12. In his diſeaſe he ſought not to
the Lord, but to the Phyſitians.</hi> Thereby he brought Gods
wrath upon himſelf.</p>
            <p>The intendment of the copulative particle in this place
is well expreſſed by this conjunction of time, <hi>Then.</hi> For
he gathered them together that ſhould help him, and <hi>then,</hi>
ſought a bleſſing of God.</p>
            <p>When he ſaw it meet that a Faſt ſhould be kept,<note place="margin">Governours muſt proclaim Faſts.</note> then
he proclaimed it, <hi>I proclaimed,</hi> ſaith he. <hi>Ezra,</hi> who did
this, was appointed by the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> under whoſe
juriſdiction all the Jews then were, to be a Governour:
For the King appointed him to ſet other Magiſtrates over
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114824:6"/>
the people. <hi>chap.</hi> 7. 25. which ſheweth that he had au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
over them. At leaſt he was, under the King, the
chief Governour of theſe Jews that went along with him.
This therefore which here he doth, is an authoritative
act. He doth it as a Governour. Governours uſe to make
proclamations.</p>
            <p>To proclaim implieth two things,</p>
            <p>1. To give publike notice and warning of a thing to
be done. This uſeth to be done openly by an Herald or
publike Crier. The<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> hebrew word implieth that it was
done by voice,</p>
            <p>2. To lay a charge upon thoſe to whom that notice is
given to obſerve the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus the ſolemn feaſts of the law at their appointed
times were proclaimed, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 4. Thus <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi>
proclaimed a faſt, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.? and the King and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> Jon. 3. 5, 7. Herein wicked <hi>Jezabel</hi> did
impiouſly imitate a pious practice, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 9.</p>
            <p>That which was here proclaimed was a faſt.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> A reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
faſt is a forbearing of bodily refreſhments to make
one fitter for pious duties.</p>
            <p>A faſt is here ſynecdochically put for praier alſo.<note place="margin">Faſting and praier muſt go together.</note>
Thus much is evident, by this phraſe added in this dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<hi>To ſeek of God a right way:</hi> and by joyning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
theſe two (<hi>verſe</hi> 23.) <hi>We faſted and beſought our God
for this.</hi> Oft are theſe two <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>praier</hi> joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
as <hi>Nehem. 1. 4. Daniel 9. 3. Luke 2. 37. Mat.</hi> 17. 21.
<hi>Act. 13. 3. &amp; 14. 23. 1 Cor.</hi> 7. 5. This word, <hi>faſt</hi> is oft uſed
ſynecdochically, for praier alſo, as 2 <hi>Chron. 20. 3. Jer.</hi>
36. 9. <hi>Jonah</hi> 3. 6. A faſt, ſimply and ſingly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in and by it ſelf, is but ſuch a <hi>bodily exerciſe as profiteth
little.</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 8. <hi>For as meat commendeth us not to God</hi>
(1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 8.) ſo nor faſting. But faſting joyned with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114824:6"/>
praier is of ſingular uſe (it being rightly and duly uſed:)
and that in three eſpeciall reſpects:</p>
            <p>1.<note place="margin">Faſting a help to praier.</note> It's a means of quickning a dull ſpirit, and rouſing
up a drouſie body.<note place="margin">In jejuniis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> quam plurimum adjuvatur ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, <hi>Aug</hi> Probae Ep. 121.</note> Ye know that eating and drinking
uſe to ſend vapours into the head which make a man
drouſie in body, and heavy in ſpirit. Now faſting pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteth
theſe impediments, and thereupon putteth
a kinde of life into a man, and maketh him to pour
out his ſpirit in praier the more ardently.</p>
            <p>2. It enableth a man to continue longer in his devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
A man after eating and drinking cannot ſo long hold
out in duties of piety as he that faſteth. Beſides that time
which uſeth to be ſpent in eating, drinking, and other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhments
and delights, is by faſting gained for praier
and other ſacred duties. Well obſerve the moſt ardent
and long continued ſupplications in Scripture, and you
ſhall finde them ſupported by faſting.</p>
            <p>3. Faſting is a viſible teſtification of our ardent praier,<note place="margin">Iejunium eſt adjuterium <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nam oratio illa eſt fortis quae fit in ſpiritu humili, &amp;c. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> Hom 15 in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</note>
and of our earneſt deſire to obtain that which we pray for:
in that, by our voluntary abſtaining from our bodily food
and other delights of the body, we ſhew, that we prefer
the thing that we pray for, before them. Yea faſting
is not only a teſtification if our humiliation, but it is
a means to humble the ſoul the more: for that is the
uſe of outward rites, both to teſtifie the inward
diſpoſition of the ſoul, and alſo to help it on the
more.</p>
            <p>The place where this religious duty was performed is
firſt indefinitely ſet down,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> under this relative, <hi>there.</hi> It
hath reference to <hi>ver.</hi> 15. where mention is made of <hi>Ezras</hi>
gathering together ſuch as ſhould go with him to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
At that place where they were gathered together,
<hi>there</hi> they kept this faſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114824:7"/>
2.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> In particular this place is ſet out by a river which
ran along by it: for it is here ſaid to be, <hi>at the river A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hava.</hi>
This name is thrice uſed in this Chapter:<note place="margin">The river <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hava.</hi>
               </note> as in
this text, in the 15, &amp; 33. verſes. We do not elſewhere
reade of this name, either in ſacred Scripture, or in any
other Authour. The Septuagint tranſlate it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Some
take <hi>Ahava</hi> to be the name of a Town: and this river
to be ſo called, becauſe it did run to <hi>Ahava</hi> (as <hi>verſ.</hi> 15.)
Many rivers are called by the names of thoſe Towns
which they run along by. This may be the ſame that is
by other Authours called <hi>Adiava. Joſephus</hi> in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh
book and fifth Chapter of the <hi>Antiquities
of the Jewes,</hi> ſaith, That this faſt was kept by
<hi>Euphrates.</hi> It may be that this river did ſtream out
of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> or into it, as ſundry rivers did in ſundry
places.</p>
            <p>But not to inſiſt upon the title,<note place="margin">A faſt kept by a river ſide.</note> certainly the place
which is here deſcribed by the river,<note place="margin">Legi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a Deo nomullos ex<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> dit<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in excelſis montium: unde intelligitur m<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> valere pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffectum, quam petitionis locum. <hi>Aug.</hi> de unit. Eccl c. 16.</note> was a fair and fit
place for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to aſſemble themſelves together in:
like that place which was by a rivers ſide near to <hi>Philippi,</hi>
where praier was wont to be made by Chriſtians, <hi>Act.</hi>
16. 13. There were in the Countrey of <hi>Babylon</hi> many
ſweet rivers, and goodly paſtures, yea and woods too.
Hereunto the Pſalmiſt alludeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. 1, 2. in theſe
words, <hi>By the rivers of Babylon there we ſate down,</hi> &amp;c. They
being many, and the place convenient, there they perform
their ſolemn ſacred duties. The affection of him that prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
is more regarded then the place.</p>
            <p>In paſſing from the charge to the ends of giving it,
we may obſerve a change of number. The charge about
ſuch a thing is thus ſet down in the ſingular number, <hi>I pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed:</hi>
But the expreſſion of the ends in the plurall, thus,
<hi>That WEE might afflict OVR ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. The former
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114824:7"/>
act of proclaiming the faſt, belonged only to the chief
Governour, which at that time <hi>Ezra</hi> was to thoſe Jews:
but the later acts, of afflicting themſelves, and ſeeking
of God a right way, were common duties appertaining
to them all; and for the good of them all: In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
the number is juſtly and fitly altered, and theſe plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals
uſed, <hi>WE, OVR, VS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which is here ſet down as one end of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,
<note place="margin">The extent of a faſt to afflict ones ſelf. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in this phraſe, <hi>That we might afflict ourſelves,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the extent of a true faſt. It muſt be a faſt that may
be felt: and that ſo farre, as they who keep it, may finde
and feel a want of that which they have forborn. This
may be one branch of a Chriſtians ſelf-deniall, volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
to forbear that which nature requires, and not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
unto it that which it craveth. <hi>Afflicting themſelves</hi>
here meant, extendeth both to mens bodies, and alſo to
their ſouls: For a mens ſelf doth not conſiſt of body on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
This extent of a faſt is by the law thus expreſſed,
<hi>Ye ſhall afflict your ſouls,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Body and ſoul afflicted.</note> Levit. 16. 29. The body is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,
when it is denied neceſſaries, ſo much and ſo
long as it is very ſenſible of the want thereof: by a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy
the ſoul alſo may therewith be afflicted. But the
ſoul is further afflicted, when it is grieved and diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
upon the apprehenſion of Gods diſpleaſure and wrath
for ſin, yea and for offending his fatherly goodnes: and
is thereupon deeply humbled and caſt down. By this
kinde of afflicting ones ſelf, the body is kept under and
brought into ſubjection,<note place="margin">Non dixit, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do &amp; punio: ſed caſtigo &amp; in ſervitudinem redigo: quod Domini eſt, non hoſtis. &amp;c. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> Hom. 23. in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>I keep under my body and bring it
into ſubjection,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 27. Here he
uſeth two words which carry much emphaſis, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I
keep under, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I bring into ſubjection. The
former word is taken from a Champion or Wreſtler that
ſtriveth for the maſtery: for it hath reference to the 25.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114824:8"/>
               <hi>verſe,</hi> where mention is made of men that ſtrive for the
maſtery. The later word hath reference to Maſters that
prudently keep their ſervants under,<note place="margin">Caſtigo corpus meum, hoc eſt, adverſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> carne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pugno. <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opnil.</hi> in los.</note> eſpecially when
they begin to wax inſolent or wanton. By the body he
means the old man, which is called a body of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi>
6. 6. and the fleſh which luſteth againſt the ſpirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Doth not this ſeem to juſtifie that which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
condemneth in this phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
or nor ſparing the body? <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt keeping the body un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the body.</note> Surely no. There is a great deal of difference
betwixt the Apoſtles minde and meaning in the one and
in the other place. For</p>
            <p>1. In the former place the word <hi>body</hi> is taken figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively
as was obſerved before. In the later, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly.</p>
            <p>2. In the former place, a man is only reſtrained from
ſuch things as might pleaſe the body, but be a preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice
to the ſoul. In the later the nature of man is
weakned.</p>
            <p>3. The beating down, mentioned in the former place
better enableth a man to holy duties: but neglecting
the body, in the later place, doth oft diſinable him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>4. The former is warranted by Gods Word, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
therein, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 22. The later is from mans vain
invention.</p>
            <p>5. The former is a matter of truth and ſincerity: the
later of hypocriſie and ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>In a word, by keeping the body under the corrupt fleſh
is tamed: and yet the ſtrength of a mans outward body
not impaired: but by neglecting the body, a mans out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
body conſiſting of fleſh and bone is weakned, and
yet the corrupt fleſh not ſubdued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:114824:8"/>
The afflicting of themſelves mentioned in my text is a
branch of that holy <hi>revenge,</hi> which is reckoned up among
the fruits of godly ſorrow, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11. and it is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of a <hi>broken ſpirit and contrite heart,</hi> which <hi>David</hi>
ſtileth <hi>the ſacrifices of God, which he will not deſpiſe,</hi> Pſal.
51. 17.</p>
            <p>Becauſe hypocrites in an apiſh imitation of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,
<note place="margin">Duties of piety to be done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> plead that they <hi>afflict their ſouls,</hi> Iſa. 58. 3. it is
here required that it be done <hi>before God. Now all things
are naked and opened unto the eyes of him</hi> (Heb. 4. 13.) As
a beaſt cut up, is in all the inward parts and intrals open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
before the Butcher: or an anatomy before the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion:
So are all the things of a man without and
within,<note place="margin">Oraturus ſedet, quod non fit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctè niſi in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecta Dei, hoc eſt, in intimo cordis. <hi>Aug.</hi> ad ſimpl. l. 2. q. 4.</note> known unto God. God diſcerneth our ſecret
thoughts and inward diſpoſition, <hi>Thou understandeth my
thoughts afarre off,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 2. It is
proper to God alone <hi>to ſearch the heart and try the reins,</hi>
Jer. 17. 10. That therefore is ſaid to be-done <hi>before God,</hi>
which is done from the heart, inwardly, ſincerely.</p>
            <p>This the ſervants of God doe the rather,<note place="margin">The Lord in ſpeciall the God of Saints.</note> becauſe God
is their God in an eſpeciall manner. <hi>Before OVR God,</hi>
ſaith this holy Prieſt and ſervant of God. Indeed the
Lord is a ſupream Sovereign over all. <hi>All are his ſervants,
Pſal.</hi> 119. 91. yet the <hi>Iſrael of God,</hi> the Church of God is
<hi>a choſen Generation, a royall Prieſthood, an holy Nation, a
peculiar People,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 9. Who now ſhould doe, that
which they undertake, <hi>before God,</hi> if not they, who have
a ſpeciall right to ſay of him, <hi>OVR God?</hi> This right
they have by vertue of their union with Chriſt: who
thus ſaith, <hi>I aſcend unto my Father and your Father, and to
my God and your God,</hi> Joh. 20. 17.</p>
            <p>Beſides by this ſpeciall relation <hi>their God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Lord is not as an Idol.</note> 
               <hi>Jehovah,</hi> who
is the only true God, is diſtinguiſhed from the gods of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114824:9"/>
the Heathen, even from idols, <hi>Which have mouths but
ſpeak not: eyes, but ſee not: ears, but hear not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi>
115. 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which followeth in theſe words,<note place="margin">To ſeek of God is to pray <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>to ſeek of him,</hi>
ſetteth down the moſt proper end of a Faſt, and of the
extent thereof, by <hi>afflicting ones ſelf,</hi> which is ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
to <hi>ſeeking of God. To ſeek of God,</hi> is all one as to pray
unto God, and call upon him. They are therefore oft
joyned together, as <hi>ſynonima,</hi> words or phraſes of one
and the ſame ſignification. <hi>Ask, and it ſhall be given you:
ſeek, and you ſhall finde,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 7. 7. I am ſought
of them that asked not for me, I am found of them that ſought
me not,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 1. In theſe and many other
like places, to ask and ſeek, are put for the ſame duty,
namely, to pray. The Metaphor of <hi>ſeeking</hi> implieth a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
uſing of means for obtaining that which we deſire.
In this reſpect the Church thus ſaith, <hi>I will ſeek him whom
my ſoul loveth,</hi> Cant. 3. 2.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe God only could give that which in my
text was ſought, they make their addreſſe to God to ſeek
of him.</p>
            <p>That which they ſeek is here in generall ſaid to be <hi>A
right way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">What a right way is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> This may be taken literally or metaphorical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
According to the letter it implieth a ſafe and proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
journey: namely, That the Lord would be pleaſed ſo
to direct them, as they might not wander out of the way:
nor by enemies, or any other means forced to fly this way
and that way, but that they might ſafely come to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
which was the end of their journey. In this ſence it is
ſaid of God, in relation to his people at another time, <hi>He
led them forth by the RIGHT WAY, that they might goe
to the city of habitation,</hi> Pſal. 107. 7. That thus much is
here intended, is evident by the reaſon of this Faſt, thus
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114824:9"/>
ſet down in the next verſe, <hi>For I was aſhamed to require of
the King a band of ſouldiers, and horſmen, to help us againſt
the enemy in the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Metaphorically a <hi>Way</hi> is put for a mans converſation
or courſe of life, and this is counted a <hi>right way,</hi> when it
is ordered according to the rule of righteouſneſſe which
is Gods Word. To this purpoſe the Pſalmiſt thus prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<hi>Make me to underſtand the way of thy precepts:</hi> And
thus promiſeth, <hi>I will runne the way of thy commandments,
when thou ſhalt enlarge my heart,</hi> Pſ. 119. 27, 32. This way is
called a <hi>good way,</hi> Jer. 6. 16. and a <hi>perfect way,</hi> Pſ. 101. 2, 6.</p>
            <p>Though the literall ſence of a proſperous journey be
here eſpecially intended: yet it may alſo be extended to
the metaphoricall ſence of a good courſe of life.<note place="margin">What to be praied for. 1 Our ſelves. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>That which they here ſeek, they ſeek for many.</p>
            <p>1. For themſelves. <hi>For VS,</hi> ſay they; for every one
is his own keeper, and hath a charge of himſelf: every
one muſt care for himſelf and for his own welfare:
and every one is to give an account of himſelf to God,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 12.</p>
            <p>2. They ſeek a right way <hi>for their little ones.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Our children <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Hereby
are meant their children: ſuch as could not ſeek their
own good. The Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>taph,</hi> is indeed
of the ſingular number, and never uſed in the plurall,
yet tranſlated in the plurall, <hi>little ones:</hi> for it is
a collective word, and ſignifieth a company of children,
and of ſuch as can ſcarce go. Or if they do go, they do it
weakly and ſtaggeringly. They waddle, as we ſpeak.
The verb that cometh from the ſame root, is applied to
the gate of haughty women, and thus tranſlated, <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
as they go,</hi> or <hi>tripping nicely,</hi> Iſa. 3. 16. The children
compriſed under the Hebrew word, were ſuch as they,
of whom God thus ſaith, <hi>There are more then ſix ſcore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114824:10"/>
thouſand perſons, that cannot diſcern betwixt their right hand
and their left,</hi> Jon. 4. 11. They that were of age and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,
whether male or female, Governours or
under government, joyned all together in the Faſt, and
are compriſed under this particle <hi>VS.</hi> But the <hi>little
ones,</hi> who could not joyn with them in that holy
duty, are here diſtinguiſhed from them, and are praied
for.</p>
            <p>3.<note place="margin">3 Our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> With little ones they joyn <hi>all their ſubſtance.</hi> That
alſo they pray for. Under this phraſe, <hi>All our ſubſtance,</hi>
cattell of all ſorts are compriſed, as bullocks, kine, horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,
camels, aſſes, ſheep, goats, even all kinde of living
and unreaſonable creatures, that they carried with them,
and were for their uſe: and all manner of houſhold ſtuff,
and other goods that they had; even the ſilver and the
gold, and veſſels that were given to the uſe of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
whereof mention is made, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. 15, 16. &amp;c.
The hebrew word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>recuſh.</hi> It uſeth to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed
from <hi>ſouls:</hi> namely, from perſons that had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
ſouls: as <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 5. where it is ſaid, <hi>That Abram
took Lot and all their ſubſtance, and the ſouls that they had
gotten:</hi> and <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. 21. where <hi>the King of Sodom ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Abram, Give me the perſons</hi> (heb. <hi>ſouls) and take the
goods</hi> (heb. <hi>ſubſtance) to thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus theſe Jews extended their humble and earneſt
ſupplication unto God,<note place="margin">Te<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peralia ſi deſuerint peten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſunt. <hi>Bern.</hi> de 4. modis erand.</note> not only for themſelves and their
children, but alſo for their outward eſtate: even their
temporall and worldly commodities.</p>
            <p>This of the meaning of the words. The logicall reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
of them follows.</p>
            <p>The Summe of the text being as you heard,<note place="margin">The reſolution of the text.</note> 
               <hi>A Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
for obtaining good ſucceſs in a weighty enterpriſe,</hi> Two
generall points are eſpecially ſet down therein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114824:10"/>
1. The <hi>Means</hi> uſed, which was a <hi>Faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2, The <hi>Ends</hi> why the means were uſed.</p>
            <p>About the means there is expreſſed,</p>
            <p>1. A <hi>Preparation</hi> thereunto.</p>
            <p>2. The <hi>Execution</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Preparation</hi> was by a <hi>Proclamation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Execution</hi> is ſet down, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Proclamation</hi> is amplified,</p>
            <p>1. By the <hi>Perſon</hi> that cauſed it: <hi>I proclaimed it,</hi> ſaith the
Governour.</p>
            <p>2. By the <hi>Place</hi> where the means was appointed to be
uſed, and that</p>
            <p>1. In generall, in this relative particle, <hi>there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. In particular, <hi>At the river Ahava.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ends were two.</p>
            <p>One ſubordinate, <hi>That we might afflict our ſelves.</hi> Here
the particles of the plurall number <hi>WEE, OVR,</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable.</p>
            <p>The other end is the moſt principall, <hi>To ſeek of
God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The former is amplified by the <hi>Perſon</hi> before whom
they afflicted themſelves, who is ſtiled their God: <hi>Before
our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The later is amplified by the <hi>ſubject matter</hi> that they
ſought, <hi>A right way:</hi> and by the <hi>Objects</hi> for which they
ſought it.</p>
            <p>The Objects were of two kindes.</p>
            <p>1. Perſons. <hi>Themſelves,</hi> and their <hi>little ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>Things.</hi> All their ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Theologicall Obſervations hence ariſing are theſe,<note place="margin">Theologicall obſervations.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>From the Perſon that enjoyned all, I obſerve, That</hi>
Publike duties muſt have their ſanction from publike Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:114824:11"/>
To ſuch Governours it belongeth to obſerve the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages
of Gods providence,<note place="margin">Rex epiſcoporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Synodum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolim convocavit. <hi>Socr.</hi> l. 5. c. 8.</note> and to conſider what warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
publike duties are by the direction of Gods Word
called for, at ſuch and ſuch times, and thereupon to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn
a publike obſervation of ſuch duties: to give war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
and liberty for performing them: and to ſee them
duly done.</p>
            <p>2. From the Proclamation I infer, That</p>
            <p>Warning is to be given before hand of publike,<note place="margin">Obſerv. 2.</note> ſolemn, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
duties.</p>
            <p>The Proclamation mentioned in the text, was made to
give all the people notice and warning of the Faſt. This
is the rather to be done, that all of all ſorts whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth
may from their ſeverall habitations aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether:
and that they may have ſome convenient time to
prepare themſelves thereto.</p>
            <p>3. From the Means here enjoyned, which was a Faſt, it
is evident, That</p>
            <p>Faſting is an eſpeciall help to extraordinary praier.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Their meeting was to pray.<note place="margin">Oratio non ſit propter jejuniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed jejunium propter oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> hom. 15. in Mat. 6.</note> Their faſting to do that
duty more powerfully. Praier is not for faſting, but fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
for praier. It is here ſaid, that they faſted <hi>to ſeek of
God a right way:</hi> and the iſſue thereof is thus expreſſed,
<hi>verſ. 23. So we fasted and beſought our God for this, and he
was intreated of us.</hi> Moſt of the powerfull and effectuall
praiers recorded in Scripture, were poured forth on a day
of faſt. Chriſt ſaith of a devil, that by no other means
can be caſt out, that it may be caſt out <hi>by praier and faſting,
Mat.</hi> 17. 21.</p>
            <p>4. From the Place where this Faſt was kept,
which was at the <hi>river Ahava:</hi> an open and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
place, never before ſet apart: It may be inferred,
That</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114824:11"/>
In time of need any convenient place may be taken for duties
of piety.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay,<note place="margin">Vt nobis mos eſt pro univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis orare, ſic &amp; ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fundimus preces. <hi>Theoph.</hi> in 1 Tim 2.</note> in time of need, becauſe when there is free liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
for people to meet together in publike places ſet apart
for publike duties, it is their duty and it will be their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
to take ſuch opportunities, and to make the beſt
uſe of them that they can. But when ſuch places cannot
be conveniently reſorted unto, bounden duties are not
thereupon to be neglected. This is to make the ſubſtance
give place to the circumſtance. Chriſts promiſe of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
with his, is thus indefinitely ſet down, <hi>Where two or
three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt
of them,</hi> Mat. 18. 20.</p>
            <p>5. From the Perſons that obſerved the duty, ſet down
in the plurall number, under this particle <hi>WE,</hi> it may be
gathered, That</p>
            <p>For obtaining common and publike bleſsings,<note place="margin">Obſerv. 5.</note> means are
joyntly to be uſed by all whom it concerns.<note place="margin">Loquebantur quaſi ex uncore: idcirco oranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fuit impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabilis &amp; effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cax ſermo. <hi>Cyp.</hi> ſerm. 6. de orat. Dom.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Proclamation here made tended, to that end,
namely to gather them all together for performing the
duty mentioned. A little after this, when another occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of performing a publike duty was given, they were
not only by Proclamation ſummoned together, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
a ſtrict penalty was laid upon ſuch as ſhould not come,
<hi>Chap.</hi> 10. 7, 8. By the aſſembling of many together, men
mutually ſtir up the zeal, and inflame the affection of one
another: and when many joyn bodies and ſpirits in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
one and the ſame duty of piety together,<note place="margin">Ex caetu &amp; congregatione multa eſt ſorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo. Vbi enim fuerint duo aut tres, &amp;c. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> hom. 10. in Heb. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0,</note> that
duty is the more honourable to God, and the more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull
and prevalent with him. If God account himſelf
honoured by one mans calling upon him, he is the more
honoured by many mens joyning together therein. As
the gathering together of many waters makes the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114824:12"/>
ſtream, and the voices of many together, the louder
ſound, ſo the joynt praiers of many. This very reaſon is
preſſed in his Majeſties Proclamation for a publike gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
ſolemn Faſt, <hi>July</hi> 3. 1625. in theſe words, <hi>In hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
hope and confidence, that when both Prince and people to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
throughout the whole Land, ſhall joyn in one common
and ſolemn Devotion, of ſending up their faithfull and repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
praiers, to Almighty God at one inſtant of time, the
ſame ſhall be more available to obtain that mercy, help and
comfort from him, which in the preſent important occaſion,
this Church and Common-wealth doe ſtand in need of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. From the ſubordinate <hi>End,</hi> which was to afflict
themſelves, I gather, That</p>
            <p>A ſolemn Faſt muſt be ſuch an one as may be felt.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For this end of old they faſted long. <hi>Esther</hi> required,
<hi>That they ſhould not eat, nor drink three daies night or day,
Eſth.</hi> 4. 16. In thoſe hot countries, they could longer
forbear food, then we in theſe cold countries can; and
therefore did forbear till they were afflicted. For this
end in <hi>Nineveh</hi> they reſtrained even their beaſts from
fodder and water, <hi>Jon.</hi> 3. 7. They did alſo put on ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth
with aſhes, and lay in ſack cloth and aſhes, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.
1, 3. All this was to afflict themſelves the more, and to
bring under their bodies.<note place="margin">Iejunium ſi diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretione rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, omnem car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis rebellionem edo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ordinarios motus in cippo claudit &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat <hi>Cypr.</hi> Ser. de Ieju<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> If a Faſt be diſcreetly order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
it will tame the rebellion of the fleſh, it will binde
and keep in compaſſe inordinate, and exorbitant moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and ſubdue immoderate appetites. It will ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain
ſuch things as might hinder praier, as the ſoul
will be much more free to flie up aloft.</p>
            <p>7. From the Perſon before whom they faſted, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<hi>Before God,</hi> I obſerve, That</p>
            <p>Duties of piety are to be performed as in Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.
<note place="margin">Obſerv. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:114824:12"/>
We ought to doe nothing, but as in Gods preſence:
ſo, as ſetting God before us. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hithhalec,</hi>
whereby <hi>Enochs</hi> walking before God is ſet out, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.
24. and which is required of <hi>Abram,</hi> Gen. 17. 1. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth
a conſtant, continuall ſetting of God before their
eies. It is of the ſeventh hebrew conjugation, which
importeth a frequent and conſtant performing of a thing.
Learned and judicious <hi>Tremellius</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> tranſlate
that word <hi>indeſinenter ambulare, continually to walk.</hi> If
we muſt in every place, and in every duty that we take in
hand, do it before God, much more muſt we ſo perform
duties of piety,<note place="margin">Deus omnium mentes volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in ipſis adhuc clauſi pectoris latebris intuetur. <hi>Cypr.</hi> Serm. 5. de lapſis</note> which have a kinde of immediate reſpect
unto God, and wherein we have immediately to do with
him. Theſe are moſt ſincerely to be done, becauſe God
beholds the very diſpoſition of men, and their purpoſes
while they are in their hearts.</p>
            <p>8. From this ſpeciall note of relation <hi>OVR,</hi> here
applied to God, thus, <hi>Before our GOD,</hi> it appeareth,
That</p>
            <p>The Lord is in ſpeciall manner the God of his Church.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Namely, of thoſe that profeſſe his name and believe
on him. Therefore ſuch do not only apply it to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
but alſo others give it unto them: as <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi>
an Heathen Monarch ſtiled the Lord, <hi>the God of Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach,
Meſhech, and Abednego,</hi> Dan. 3. 28. and <hi>Darius</hi>
another Heathen Monarch, ſaid to <hi>Daniel, Thy God
whom thou ſerveſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 20. This is a ground of ſtrong
confidence to believers.</p>
            <p>9. From the <hi>principall End</hi> of the Faſt, which was,
<hi>To ſeek of God,</hi> or to pray to God, it is moſt manifeſt,
That</p>
            <p>Praier is the most principall means of obtaining bleſsing
bleſsing from God.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114824:13"/>
This means God himſelf hath preſcribed and enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
for that end:<note place="margin">Quod Deus per ſuam promiſit clementiam per ſanctorum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet preces. <hi>Hier.</hi> Com. in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.</note> There unto hath he made many precious
promiſes. Here upon Saints in all ages have uſed this
means, and found it to be effectuall. That which through
his grace he promiſeth, upon the praiers of his Saints, he
performeth.</p>
            <p>10. From the ſubject matter that is deſired, which is
<hi>a right way,</hi> it appears, That</p>
            <p>A proſperous journey may be ſought of God.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Men in their journies are ſubject to many dangers.
The divine Providence can keep them fare from all their
dangers: Yea, he can ſo order it, that by miſtaking of a
way, they may avoid ſome dangerous plots of enemies
againſt them <hi>Auſtine</hi> relates a ſtory much tending to that
purpoſe;<note place="margin">Nobi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-ipſis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidit, ut in quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam bivio falle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remur, &amp; non iremus per eum locum, ubi ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riens tranſitum noſtrum Doxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtarum <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s armata ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat: at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ita factum eſt, ut eoquo tendeba mus, per devium circuitum veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus: cogni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> infidiis il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, nos gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tularemur er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſe, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inde gratias agere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Leo. <hi>Aug.</hi> Enchid ad Lau. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</note> That in his journey he came to a two want
way, or to a place which went two waies. In that which
led moſt directly to his journies end, an armed troop of
the Donatiſts lay, to ſeize upon him; but he ignorantly
fell into the other way, whereby he eſcaped that troop,
and going the wrong way, though fartheſt about, came
ſafely to his journies end, and praiſed God for that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake
of his way. God giveth to ſuch as ſeek it of him,
Angels to keep them in all their waies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. 11. The
Heathen ſuppoſed that there were certain gods who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
ſuch as called upon them in their right way, and
gave them a proſperous journey. Theſe they called
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> But indeed it is <hi>Jehovah</hi> only that is properly the
director of our waies, <hi>In all thy waies acknowledge him, and
he ſhall direct thy paths,</hi> Prov. 3. 6. This may alſo be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
to the methaphoricall interpretation of this phraſe, <hi>A
right way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>11. From the firſt ſort of <hi>Perſons</hi> for whom they pray,
which were <hi>themſelves,</hi> I collect, That</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:114824:13"/>
Men muſt eſpecially ſeek bleſsing for themſelves.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Every man is neareſt to himſelf: and a mans ſelf is the
rule of the love of his neighbour: for thus ſaith the Law,
<hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> Mat. 22. 39. I may
make from hence ſuch an inference as the Apoſtle doth
from a Biſhops ruling his own houſe, <hi>If a man know not
how to rule his own houſe, how ſhall he take care of the Church
of God?</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 5. In like manner if a man know not
how to ſeek his own good, how ſhall he take care for the
good of others?</p>
            <p>12. From the ſecond ſort of <hi>Perſons,</hi> which were their
<hi>littl ones,</hi> I further obſerve, That</p>
            <p>Bleſsing is to be ſought for our young children.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Even for ſuch as cannot ſeek it for themſelves. Their
welfare is a means of continuing not the world only, but
the Church alſo in the world. We are mortall, and ſhall
not alwaies abide here to ſerve the Lord. As our fathers,
who ſerved God in their generations, are gone, ſo ſhall
we after a ſhort time: God knows how ſoon. But by
procuring Gods bleſſing on our <hi>little ones,</hi> they may grow
up, they may know God and ſerve him in their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
after we are taken from them. Thus may the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
God be everlaſtingly ſerved by mortall men: one
generation ſerving him after another. To ſharpen our
praiers, and ſtrengthen our faith in craving a bleſſing for
our <hi>little ones,</hi> we may plead before God that which
God himſelf ſais of the children of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that they
were <hi>born to him,</hi> and were <hi>his children,</hi> Ezek. 16. 20, 21.
On this ground, though our unworthineſſe make us fear
that God may curſe them rather then bleſſe them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they are <hi>ours,</hi> yet we may herewith uphold our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
that they are Gods children, born to him: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
pray that God for his own ſake would bleſſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:114824:14"/>
13. From the <hi>Things</hi> for which God was ſought,
which are here called, <hi>All their ſubſtance,</hi> it appears,
That</p>
            <p>Bleſsing may be ſought of God for our temporall estate.<note place="margin">Obſerv. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Petition of the Lords praier (<hi>Give us this
day our daily bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omnia iſta bona ſunt, &amp; Dei munera ſunt. Ne putetis quod aliquis illa pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit dare niſi u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Deus. <hi>Aug.</hi> Enar in Pſ. 35.</note> Mat. 6. 11.) giveth evidence to the
truth hereof. Though, through mans ordinary abuſe
of the goods of this world, Chriſt ſtileth them, <hi>Mammon
of unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> yet he adviſeth us to <hi>make to our ſelves
friends thereof,</hi> Luk. 16. 9. They are neceſſary for the
very being of our bodies. Life, health, ſtrength, are
preſerved by them. They may be a means of continuing
the Miniſtery of Gods Word and Ordinances among us:
and we by them may be many waies helped, even about
the ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the diſtinct Inſtructions which this text af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth.
They are many and weighty. It cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
that I ſhould handle them all at this time in any
large manner. I will therefore collect one generall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,
wherein the main ſcope and drift of the text
ſhall be ſet forth: and which ſhall compriſe under it, moſt,
if not all, of the points before noted. It is this,</p>
            <p>In a matter extraordinary,<note place="margin">The generall Doctrine.</note> extraordinary means muſt be
uſed.</p>
            <p>To ſhew that this doctrine is the main intendment of
my text, two things are to be demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>1. The <hi>Caſe,</hi> that it was extraordinary.</p>
            <p>2. The <hi>Means,</hi> that they were extraordinary.</p>
            <p>Each of theſe may be made manifeſt in ſeven particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
branches a piece.</p>
            <p>1. Theſe Jews were in a <hi>ſtrange land.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary caſe of the Jews.</note> So is the land of
their captivity ſtiled, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 137. 4. where thus they ſay, <hi>How
ſhall we ſing the Lords ſong in a ſtrange land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114824:14"/>
2. They were at this time <hi>captives:</hi> for notwithſtanding
this and a former return from the place of their captivity,
they were, even after this, counted and called, <hi>children
of the captivity,</hi> Chap. 10. 7, 16.</p>
            <p>3. The name of a Jew, was odious among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.
Many envied them for their religion and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
ſake. When <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> went to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> he found
<hi>adverſaries, Ezra</hi> 4. 1. when afterward <hi>Nehemiah</hi> went,
he found thoſe who much <hi>envied that there was a man
come to ſeek the welfare of the children of Iſrael,</hi> Neh. 2. 10.
<hi>Haman</hi> could ſuggeſt to the King of <hi>Perſia, That the laws
of the Jews were divers from all people, and that it was not
for the Kings profit to ſuffer them,</hi> Eſth. 3. 8. <hi>Yea many laid
wait for Ezra and his company in the way,</hi> verſ. 31.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>They had no outward guard of horſe or foot, for</hi>
Ezra was aſhamed to require of the King a band of ſouldiers
and horſmen to help them againſt the enemy in the way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they had ſpoken unto the King, ſaying, The hand of our
God is upon all them for good, that ſeek him, <hi>verſ. 22. Thus
they engaged Gods honour in this caſe, which maketh it
the more extraordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. Of themſelves they could not go the right way.
Their ſeeking this of God implies as much.</p>
            <p>6. They had the care of many little ones lying
upon them. This made their caſe the more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</p>
            <p>7. They had a great charge with them: as their own
cattel and goods: and a great ſumme of ſilver and gold,
which the <hi>King and his Councellours had freely offered unto
the God of Iſrael: and ſtore of veſſels for the ſervice of God,</hi>
v. 33. Chap. 7. 15.</p>
            <p>Do not all theſe particular circumſtances make their
preſent caſe to be more then an ordinary caſe?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114824:15"/>
Anſwerably the means which they uſed were extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary:
as is evident by a like number of particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>1. A publike <hi>Proclamation</hi> was made to call them all
together,<note place="margin">The extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary means which the Jevvs uſed.</note> and to give them warning before hand that they
might come prepared. Proclamations uſe not to be made
but in weighty matters.</p>
            <p>2. A <hi>Faſt</hi> was enjoyned. Faſting hath been before no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to be an extraordinary act of piety.</p>
            <p>3. For want of a Synagogue, or a Temple, they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
their faſt in the open air <hi>by a river ſide.</hi> This was more
then uſuall.</p>
            <p>4. They extend their faſt to <hi>afflict themſelves,</hi> that they
might ſenſibly feel it.</p>
            <p>5. They do it not in appearance only, but really, in
truth <hi>before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. They do not only wiſh for what they needed, but
they earneſtly <hi>ſeek</hi> it of God.</p>
            <p>7. They plead a ſpeciall relation betwixt God and
themſelves, in this phraſe, <hi>OVR God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lay together the particulars of their <hi>Caſe,</hi> and of the
<hi>Means</hi> that they uſed, and you ſhall finde the one and the
other to be extraordinary: yea you may alſo obſerve all
the particulars of the text couched within this doctrine, <hi>In
a matter extraordinary, extraordinary means muſt be
uſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This courſe hath Gods Church taken throughout all
ages,<note place="margin">Extraordinary caſes. 1. Obtaining or regaining bleſſings.</note> in all manner of extraordinary caſes: and that</p>
            <p>1. For obtaining good things.</p>
            <p>2. For removing evils: and both theſe about ſpirituall
and temporall, publike and private matters.</p>
            <p>For <hi>good things,</hi> extraordinary praier hath been
made, when Saints and ſervants of God have ſeen them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114824:15"/>
needfull <hi>then</hi> to be <hi>granted;</hi> or when they have been
<hi>withheld:</hi> or when they have been <hi>withdrawn</hi> and taken
away.</p>
            <p>This may be exemplified in ſundry particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> earneſtly praied for a good <hi>Governour</hi> to ſucceed
him,<note place="margin">Speciall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily praied for.</note> 
               <hi>Numb. 27. 16. Chriſt</hi> ſpent a whole night in praier
immediately before his chuſing of <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> Luk. 6. 12,
13. The Apoſtles ordained Elders in every Church <hi>with
praier and faſting,</hi> Act. 14. 23. The <hi>Church faſted and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
when <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> were ſeparated to the work,
whereunto God called them, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 3. The like courſe
ſhould be taken by us in ordaining Miniſters, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
Officers in their ſeverall places: yea and in enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing
weighty affairs of more then ordinary concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Much more ought this courſe to be taken when deſired
and expected bleſſings are <hi>withheld.</hi> This was <hi>Hannahs</hi>
caſe, which mov'd her to <hi>weap</hi> and <hi>faſt,</hi> and <hi>pour out her
ſoul before the Lord, 1 Sam.</hi> 1. 7, 15.</p>
            <p>Moſt of all is this to be done, when bleſſings are <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn</hi>
and taken away: eſpecially if they be ſpirituall
bleſſings. The ſenſible preſence, powerfull aſſiſtance,
and ſweet comfort of the Spirit, being <hi>withdrawn</hi> from
<hi>David,</hi> upon the great ſins which he committed in the
caſe of <hi>Bathſheba</hi> and her husband, he penned the one and
fiftieth Pſalme, which manifeſteth an extraordinary
wreſtling with the Lord, to have thoſe bleſſings reſtored
to him again. His wreſtling in this caſe was like <hi>Jacobs,</hi>
who would not let the Lord go unleſſe he bleſſed him,<note place="margin">2. Preventing or removing evils.</note>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. 26.<note place="margin">Hoc eſt totum quod dicitur malum, i.e. pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum, &amp; poe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a peccati <hi>Aug.</hi> de ver relig. c. 11</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Evils</hi> againſt which extraordinary praier is to be made,
are ſins or judgements.</p>
            <p>Againſt-ſins, ſuch praiers are to be made, to prevent
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114824:16"/>
them, or redreſſe them. For preventing ſinne, Chriſt
commandeth his Diſciples to <hi>watch and pray, that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
not into temptation,</hi> Mat. 24. 41. By temptations men
are drawn to ſin. By being freed from the temptation
or aſſiſted and ſupported in the temptation, ſin may be
<hi>prevented,</hi> Gen. 20. 6. &amp; 39. 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For redreſſing ſin after we are fallen into it, two things
are to be praied for:</p>
            <p>One that God would be pleaſed to pardon it. It was
an earneſt praier in this caſe that he poured out, who thus
praied, <hi>For thy names ſake, O Lord, pardon mine iniquitie:
for it is great,</hi> Pſal. 25. 11. And again thus, <hi>According to
the multitude of thy tender mercies, blot out my tranſgreſsions,
Pſal.</hi> 51. 1.</p>
            <p>The other is, that God would work in us repentance,
as he who thus praied, <hi>Turn thou me, and I ſhall be turned:
for thou art the Lord my God,</hi> Jer. 31. 18. The more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
the temptations unto ſin, whereunto we are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
are, and the more hainous the ſins are whereinto
we have fallen, the more earneſt ought our praiers, in this
caſe to be.</p>
            <p>Judgements,<note place="margin">How judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be praied againſt.</note> againſt which extraordinary praier is to
be made, are ſuch as are threatned, and in that reſpect to be
feared; or executed, and in that reſpect felt. Againſt
the former,<note place="margin">Ipſe Dominus frequenter ſuam mutat ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. Nam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſuerat percu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere morte &amp; perdere populu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed poſtea roga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus à Moyſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliatus eſt populo ſuo <hi>Ambr</hi> Offic. l 3. c. 12.</note> the King and people of <hi>Nineveh</hi> faſted and
cried mightily unto God, <hi>Jon.</hi> 3. 7, 8. Thus was that
doom reverſed and judgment prevented. The like may be
done in a preparation to a judgment before it be put into
execution. <hi>Haman</hi> had prepared a terrible maſſacre to
deſtroy all the Jews: but before his cruell plot began to
be put in execution, <hi>Mordecai, Eſther,</hi> and all the Jews,
<hi>Faſted three daies together</hi> (Eſth. 4. 16, 17.) Thus the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
of that judgement, ſo prepared, was prevented.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:114824:16"/>
Execution of judgement may be conſidered either in
the beginning, or in the full accompliſhment of it. A
judgement was begun when the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> were gathered
together to <hi>Mizpeh: but Samuel cried unto the Lord, and
the Lord deſtroied them before Iſrael,</hi> 1 Sam. 7. 7, 10. On
<hi>Manaſseh</hi> the judgement was executed to the full, in that
he was <hi>taken</hi> by his enemy, <hi>bound with fetters, and carried
to Babylon: but when he was in affliction he beſought the
Lord his God, and humbled himſelf greatly,</hi> and ſo was
freed from that judgement: <hi>For he was brought again into
his kingdome,</hi> 2 Chron. 33. 12, 13. As extraordinary prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
in theſe and other like caſes, is to be made on our own
behalf, ſo alſo on the behalf of others. <hi>Moſes</hi> his mighty
praiers (by one of which God was moved to ſay, <hi>Let me
alone:</hi> and in another <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf was moved thus to
ſay, <hi>If thou wilt not forgive their ſin, blot me, I pray thee,
out of thy book,</hi> &amp;c.) were made in the behalf of others,
<hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 10, 32.</p>
            <p>Weighty grounds there are to preſſe this point of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
praier in extraordinary caſes.<note place="margin">Reaſons for extraordinary praier.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1.<note place="margin">1 Thereby is ſhewed how we are affected with Gods dealing with us</note> We ſhew thereby that we take notice of Gods
foot-ſteps, that is, of his carriage towards us, and of his
dealing with us.</p>
            <p>2. We give evidence that we are anſwerably affected:
In that according to the need wherein we ſtand of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
we doe the more earneſtly ſeek it: and the more
heavily we feel his hand lying upon us, the more deeply
we are humbled, and doe the more earneſtly deſire that
it may be removed from us. Surely ſuch a diſpoſition
cannot be but very acceptable unto God. God much
approves thoſe who prize his favour and bleſſing above
all other things, and who are much grieved upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion
of his diſpleaſure againſt them. Now extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114824:17"/>
praier, for obtaining his favour and bleſſing, or
for removing his wrath and judgements, gives proof of
ſuch a diſpoſition.<note place="margin">Nonne oratio ſic tepida eſt, vel potius fri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gida, &amp; pene nulla, ut ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hoc in nobis cum dolore adverta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus? <hi>Aug</hi> ad Simplic l. 1. quaeſt. 2.</note> There are many who (like mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſes
ſtill going round in their uſuall tract) content
themſelves with an ordinary manner of praying: and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
take the occaſions which by the divine providence
are offered for extraordinary praier. So cold are their
praiers and liveleſſe, as they are never troubled at the
fruitleſneſſe of them, but think all is well in that they
are not ſuch Atheiſts as never call upon God. Theſe
plainly diſcover that ſmall, or no notice at all, that they
take of Gods dealing with them. Yea they doe further
diſcover a ſenſleſſe and wretched diſpoſition, in that they
care not to uſe the means that are ſanctified for obtaining
the good things whereof they ſtand in need, or removing
the evils, which lie heavy upon them. Thus it comes
to paſſe that they want many bleſſings, which otherwiſe
they might have: and lie long under many judgements,
which might have been removed, if the fore-ſaid means
had been duly uſed.</p>
            <p>2. Another ground to preſſe extraordinary praier in
an extraordinary caſe,<note place="margin">2 Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry praier is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary powerfull.</note> is Gods uſual dealing with men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to their dealing with him:<note place="margin">Ora fortiter, &amp; dic Deo, In ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatibus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rue me. Tunc fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuntur iſtae neceſſitates. <hi>Aug.</hi> Nedib. ep. 71.</note> even according to the
manner and meaſure of ſeeking this or that of him. Praier
more then ordinary is more then ordinarily powerfull. In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance
this in my Text: for thus it is ſaid, <hi>ver. 23. We faſted
and beſought our God for this, and he was intreated of us.</hi>
Many and admirable have been the effects of praier and
faſting recorded in Gods Word: and thoſe ſometimes
for preventing or removing great judgements: and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
for obtaining or regaining ſingular bleſſings. Proofs
hereof you heard before. This in generall I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
affirm, That praier and faſting, being rightly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114824:17"/>
was never uſed in vain: but ſome ſpeciall and
extraordinary effect followed thereupon.</p>
            <p>Though that particular for which <hi>David</hi> praied and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted,
<hi>and lay all night upon the earth,</hi> namely, the life of
his ſick childe, were not granted (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 16, 18.) yet
was not that extraordinary means, which he uſed, in vain:
For</p>
            <p>1. That humiliation, ſupplication and afflicting of
himſelf, was a ſervice warranted by Gods Word, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
unto God.</p>
            <p>2. Though God reſtored not to the childe his naturall
life: yet he beſtowed upon it eternall life: which
may be inferred out of theſe words which <hi>David</hi> uſed
to comfort himſelf, <hi>I ſhall goe to him,</hi> 2 Samuel 12.
23.</p>
            <p>3. God gave him another ſon, and that of the ſame
mother, a <hi>Salomon,</hi> a <hi>Jedediah</hi> (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 24, 25.) <hi>A
Prince of peace, beloved of the Lord,</hi> who, by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment
ſucceeded <hi>David</hi> on the Throne. It is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable
how the Lord had reſpect to <hi>Ahabs humbling
himſelf before God:</hi> for thereby he was moved to
put off the judgement denounced, all his daies, 1 <hi>King.</hi>
21. 29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True it is, that hypocrites have thus expoſtulated this
caſe with God,</hi> Wherefore have we faſted, and thou ſeest not?
Wherefore have we afflicted our ſouls, and thou takeſt no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?
<hi>But the fault is there laid upon themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 3.</note> That they
faſted for ſtrife and debate, <hi>&amp;c. Their faſt was not ſuch an
one as the Lord had choſen:</hi> So as the Lords hand was not
ſhortned, that it could not ſave: nor his ear heavy, that it
could not hear: but their iniquities had ſeparated between them
and their God, and their ſins had hid his face from them, that he
would not hear, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:114824:18"/>
Let us therefore that do what is warrantable, do it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly
and fervently: ſo may we do it in faith, and be
be ſure to have it accepted. <hi>All things are poſsible to him
that beleeveth,</hi> Mark 9. 23. Surely we fail of much bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
that we might receive from our praiers, for want of
faith.</p>
            <p>3. I might here adde,<note place="margin">3 By extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary praier extraordinary honour is done to God.</note> that by faſting and praier, which is
an extraordinary humbling of our ſelves before God, and
an extraordinary manner of craving bleſſing of him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
honour is done unto him: for the more we
humble our ſelves for his diſpleaſure, and ſtoop under his
ſtrokes, the greater teſtimony we give, not only to the
greatneſſe of his wrath and indignation: but alſo to the
juſtice and equity of his judgements: and the more
earneſtly we call on him for favour and bleſſing, the
greater evidence we give of our high eſteem of them.
Now by how much the more God is acknowledged and
juſtified in his judgements, and by how much the more
Gods favour and bleſſings are priſed, by ſo much the
more is the Lord glorified. For Gods honour is much
ſet forth in and by mans acknowledgement of his juſtice
and mercy.<note place="margin">Nihil magis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum eſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quam ut in omni opere ejus Dei gloria praedicetur. <hi>Hier.</hi> Com. in 1 Cor. 10.</note> And who would not doe to his uttermoſt
what he can to ſet forth the Lords honour? This third
ground of the fore-ſaid duty is the weightieſt of all the
reſt.</p>
            <p>If theſe motives be not of force to enforce this duty
of extraordinary ſupplication, in an extraordinary
caſe, I know not what motives may be of force to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force
a duty.</p>
            <p>Come we now therefore to the Application of the
Point.</p>
            <p>1. Too great cauſe of juſt complaint may here be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
up,<note place="margin">Lamentation for mens ſleighting faſts</note> by reaſon of mens ſlight and careleſſe obſerving
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114824:18"/>
thoſe means which are warranted and preſcribed by
Gods Word, for pacifying his wrath, and procuring
his favour. The Lord may juſtly upbraid to us our
faſts, as he did to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> before mentioned, <hi>Iſa.</hi>
58. 3, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This complaint may juſtly be taken up, not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the prophaner ſort of people, but alſo againſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
that look <hi>Sion-ward.</hi> There be of them that on our
monethly daies of faſt, not only forbear to joyn with the
aſſembly of Gods people in thoſe ſolemn ſacred duties:
but alſo follow their ſecular affairs: yea their pleaſures
and paſtimes, in a kinde of diſlike, if not a deteſtation of
theſe duties. I will not lay to their charge their diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowing
of theſe duties, as if ſo be they thought faſting
and praier unlawfull: but their diſeſteem of our moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
daies enjoyned by publike authority.<note place="margin">The ground of our monthly faſts.</note> The authority
was firſt his Majeſties Proclamation, ſtraitly charging
and commanding, <hi>That a Generall, Publike and Solemn
Faſt be kept and held on the laſt Wedneſday of every month, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the troubles in the Kingdome of Ireland.</hi> This Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
was given the eight day of <hi>January</hi> in the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth
of his Majeſties reign. It hath been alſo ratified
by ſundry Orders and Ordinances of Parliament, for a
due obſerving thereof; and it hath continued now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
ſeven whole years, and that upon juſt and weighty
cauſes: for the very ground of that Proclamation ſtill
remaineth, namely, <hi>The lamentable and diſtreſſed eſtate
of Ireland.</hi> Now why this monethly faſt ſhould not be
duly obſerved, I ſee no good reaſon. It may be, that
it is diſeſteemed by many, becauſe it is enjoyned by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.
But that ſeems to me a ſtrange reaſon, that
that which is a ground warranted by Gods Word (as
out of this text we have formerly ſhewed) ſhould be a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114824:19"/>
reaſon to ſlight it. I know not how it comes to paſſe,
but ſo it is, that mens mindes are averſe from ſuch things
as are enjoyned by authority, though they be things
lawfull and agreeable to Gods Word. Never were Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
and Ordinances of Parliament more ſlighted then
now, and that in things that concern their own good. <hi>O
tempora! O mores!</hi> To what times are we reſerved? What
are the mindes and manners of men?</p>
            <p>But it may be,<note place="margin">Faſts may be continued while the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion remains</note> that another thing ſcruples their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,
namely, the ſet times of faſt, that it is ſuch a day
in every moneth.</p>
            <p>I grant that if there were not a continued occaſion of
this conſtant courſe, there might be ſome ground of
ſcruple: but that particular ground of enjoyning this
monethly faſt, ſtill remaining, and other weighty grounds
alſo more nearly concerning us, namely, the troubles of
our own Kingdome, why ſhould we not perſevere in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
the means for averting Gods wrath, and the fearfull
effects thereof from us? That which is recorded of the
<hi>Jews</hi> annuall faſting, in certain ſet moneths, ſeventy
years together (becauſe the judgements, which moved
them firſt to take up thoſe faſts, continued ſo long) may
be a warrant for our continued monethly faſts. For they
are ſo mentioned by the Prophet (<hi>Zech.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Publike faſts in former times rare,</hi> Quid mirum ſi Chriſtianis temporibus iſte mundus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſervus jam ſciens vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſui &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens digna pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis vapulat multis <hi>Aug.</hi> vict. ep. 122.</note> 5. &amp; 8. 19.) as
they are rather ratified then diſavowed.</p>
            <p>No marvel that Gods judgements have ſo long lien
upon us, and our neighbouring Nations; ſeeing the means
of removing them are by moſt either deſpiſed, or too
much ſlighted.</p>
            <p>The great complaint of pious Chriſtians in former
times was, that publike faſts were not enjoyned by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
authority. Sometimes a dozen, ſometimes more
years paſſed in this Land and Kingdome without any
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114824:19"/>
publike faſts, and yet ſundry Parliaments called in thoſe
years: ſundry Armies ſent forth, and ſundry judgements
inflicted. I can remember a ſolemn faſt proclaimed,
and moſt ſolemnly kept in the year 1588. upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
of that Spaniſh Armado, that carried the ſtile of
<hi>Invincible.</hi> Admirable was the bleſſing that followed
upon that faſt: for ſoon after, that proud <hi>Armado</hi> was
ſtrangely diſſipated. I doe not well remember another
publike faſt betwixt that and the firſt year of King <hi>James,</hi>
wherein was ſuch a raging Plague, as we have not heard
of the like before in this Land. Thereupon a weekly faſt
was enjoyned by publike authority, till it pleaſed God to
remove that plague.</p>
            <p>Very few publike faſts were betwixt that and another
greater plague, in the year, 1625. when there was alſo a
weekly faſt enjoyned by publike authority: at which
time God gave a very gracious return to the praiers of his
people: for the plague decreaſed much faſter then it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed,
and in ſhort time from the number of five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
two hundred and five that died in one week, it came
ſo utterly to ceaſe, as not one at all to die of that ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that in thoſe times wherein there were ſo
few or no faſts, God exceedingly bleſſed this Kingdom,
I anſwer:</p>
            <p>1. That God might put off his diſpleaſure for neglect
of thoſe duties, till after and worſer times, and that he
may in theſe our daies, remember that neglect. Such an
anſwer doth <hi>Jeremy</hi> give to the men of <hi>Judah</hi> that made
ſuch an objection, <hi>Jer. 44. 17, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Though there were not ſuch extraordinary means
publikely uſed:<note place="margin">Frequent faſts of old in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate.</note> yet they were by pious and devout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
privately, and that frequently and fervently uſed.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114824:20"/>
Never was a Parliament called, never was an Army ſent
forth, never was there any publike weighty occaſion,
but that ſuch Chriſtians as are before mentioned, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
together, by praier and faſting, to ſeek a bleſſing
of God. I well remember, that at that very time when
the Gun-powder treaſon was diſcovered (a Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ſummoned) there were many aſſemblies that by prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
and faſting, earneſtly ſought of God a bleſſing upon
that Parliament. Have we not cauſe to judge, that God
had a gracious reſpect to the praiers of his children, who
almoſt miraculouſly diſcovered ſuch a dangerous, devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh
and matchleſſe treaſon, as the Gun-powder treaſon
was.</p>
            <p>Thorow the good providence of God, we have had
more faſts by publike authority enjoyned, in the reign of
our preſent Sovereign, eſpecially ſince the beginning of
this Parliament, then before time from the beginning of
the Reformation of Religion. But they have been ſo
ſleightly and careleſly performed, as we have cauſe to
fear, that this among other ſins, hath been one that hath
cauſed Gods heavy wrath ſo long to lie upon us. This is
a lamentation, and ſhall be for a lamentation.</p>
            <p>But to leave complaints,<note place="margin">The weighty occaſion of this daies faſt.</note> the Doctrine which you have
heard largely handled, doth juſtifie that courſe which
the great Councel of this Land hath taken about this daies
faſt. The means that we uſe, hath been ſhewed to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary.
He that ſees not that the caſe wherein we
now are, and the occaſion of this daies ſolemnity is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary,
is blinde, and cannot ſee far off.</p>
            <p>I will not now ſtand to aggravate this civil war (the
ſevereſt of Gods judgements) nor bring to your minde
the houſes,<note place="margin">The calamities of theſe times.</note> Towns, and Cities that have been burnt or
plundered, or ſpoiled: nor the diſtreſſed eſtates of many
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114824:20"/>
who in a night of a rich <hi>Job</hi> have bin made a poor <hi>Iob:</hi> nor
the abundance of bloud that hath been ſhed: nor the alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
of affections, and bitter contentions that have been
betwixt ſuch as have been near in bloud and alliance, in
neighbourhood and friendſhip, yea alſo and betwixt
ſuch as profeſſe in truth and ſincerity to ſeek the right
and perfect way of the LORD: neither will I here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
upon the errours, hereſies, and blaſphemies that in
theſe daies are publiſhed: nor the great rent that is
made in this Church by ſchiſme. Theſe and other like
occaſions of humbling our ſelves deeply before the
LORD, and of crying mightily unto him, I now let
paſſe.</p>
            <p>The particular occaſion of faſting and praying on this
day is to obtain a bleſſing from heaven upon the Treaty
betwixt his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and our <hi>Parliament,</hi> that is now tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
Gods bleſſing agreed upon.</p>
            <p>Surely this is a very extraordinary caſe, and that in
regard of the <hi>Neceſsity, Excellency, and Difficulty of the
matter undertaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Such have been the evils of this civil war (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
a taſte was given before) and many of them do ſo
continue to increaſe more and more,<note place="margin">The neceſſity of a Treaty.</note> as there is a kinde
of neceſſity of a good accommodation for compoſing
our differences: and for ſetling a ſafe and well-grounded
Peace: which cannot better be effected then by a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
Such diviſions, ſuch contentions, ſuch confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
there are in this Kingdome, as it is in danger to be
utterly ruined, if ſome ſpeedy courſe be not taken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair,
cloſe up and heal the breaches thereof. It was in
the caſe of a civill warre, that the chief Commander on
the one ſide, ſaid to the other, <hi>Shall the ſword devour for
ever? Knoweſt thou not that it will be bitterneſſe in the later
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114824:21"/>
end,</hi> 2 Sam. 2. 26. Bitterneſſe there muſt needs be in
ſuch a kinde of warre, becauſe on which ſide ſoever the
victory falleth, <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> members of the Church, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours
of the faith are deſtroied. Though the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
did preſſe that bitterneſſe, yet the Conquerour
gave over thereupon. O that they who thorow the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
providence have been kept from the extremity of
this warre, would lay to heart the condition of them
that have felt it: not of them only who have been on
the other ſide: but of many alſo who have been on our
own ſide! They would then ſee a neceſſity of a fair com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
our differences, and of yeelding to an accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<hi>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad aras,</hi> ſo far as may ſtand with the truth
and purity of Religion.</p>
            <p>2. The main and principall matter of this Treaty,<note place="margin">Weighty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on.</note> ſhews
the excellency, weight and worth of it. It concerns
King,<note place="margin">I might here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the benefits of peace. But theſe have bin diſtinctly and largely ſet down in my Treatiſe of <hi>the Churches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,</hi> on <hi>Exo.</hi> 17. 16. §. 96.</note> Parliament and Kingdome. The prerogatives of
the one, priviledges of the other, and liberties of the
third. It concerns the Church and Common-wealth,
and the good government of both. It concerns the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
of a diſtracted Kingdome in peace and quietneſſe:
and the eſtabliſhing of Religion in truth, purity and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.
It concerns the reconciling of adverſe parties, even
ſuch as have been in open hoſtility one againſt another;
and thereby to put and end to a long, unnaturall, bloudy,
civil war. What more weighty matters can be treated
about.</p>
            <p>3. The difficulty of bringing this Treaty to a good iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue
appears in theſe and other like particulars:<note place="margin">The great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles that lie in the vvay.</note> That prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
of old learned, muſt be unlearned: That long reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
judgements in ſundry caſes, muſt be upon better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,
unreſolved: That <hi>jus divinum</hi> held in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
caſes muſt be cleared and demonſtrated to which caſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114824:21"/>
it belongeth: That inbred ſcruples of conſcience muſt
be rooted out: That imbittered and alienated affections
muſt be altered: That incenſed and exaſperated ſpirits
muſt be calmed: That hoſtile friends muſt be reconciled:
That vaſt debts muſt be diſcharged: That the arrears of
numberleſſe ſouldiers muſt be ſatisfied: That reſtitution
of ſhips, goods, lands, heriditaments, livings, offices, and
other intereſts muſt be made: That indemnity for mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
outrages muſt be given, and a generall oblivion of
wrongs muſt be granted; and burthen of the Kingdome
taken off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now who can hope that theſe and ſundry other diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
can be removed for ſetling a good laſting peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">God can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties.</note>
               <hi>Yet ſurely they muſt be removed, or a ſound peace will
hardly be ſetled. God to whom all things are poſſible
can do it.</hi> He can exalt every valley, and make low every
mountain and hill:<note place="margin">Iſa 40. 4.</note> He can make ſtraight that which is crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and the rough places plain. <hi>He can cauſe</hi> the Wolf to
dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard to lie down with the
Kid:<note place="margin">11. 6, 7.</note> and the Calf, and the young Lion, and the fatling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and a little Childe to lead them: and the Cow and the
Bare to feed: their young ones to lie down together: and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to eat ſtraw like the Oxe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The God that hath promiſed to work ſuch ſtrange
works can remove the afore-ſaid difficulties,</hi>
               <note place="margin">God more then ordinarily to be ſought unto</note> 
               <hi>and greater
then them. But he is to be ſought unto, and the more
difficult the caſe is, the more earneſt and fervent muſt our
praiers be.</hi> When Herod had apprehended Peter, and put him
in priſon, and delivered him to four quaternians of ſouldiers,
intending to bring him forth to the people, and to ſlay him:
praier was made without ceaſing, or inſtant and earneſt praier
was made of the Church unto God for him, <hi>and God ſo heard
their praier as he delivered</hi> Peter, <hi>Act.</hi> 12. 4, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:114824:22"/>
Who would have thought that the miſchievous device
of <hi>Haman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſter</hi> cum ha beret neceſſitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> interveniendi pro populo ſuo, quem Rex ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in regn ejus eſſet, juſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat trucidari, oravit ad Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum: cogebat enim eam mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na neceſſitas, &amp;c <hi>Aug.</hi> de Gra &amp; lib. arb. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 21.</note> ſhould have turned to ſuch an advantage unto
the Church as it did? But that was from the Lord, and
obtained by faſting and praier, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4. 17.</p>
            <p>O let us make earneſt and inſtant praier without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
to our God, that he would ſend down his Spirit to
be a Commiſſioner among other Commiſſioners that are
to treat about peace: yea that his Spirit would be in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of the Commiſſioners, and in our King and Parliament
alſo, to bring their ſpirits to yeeld to that which may make
to a good peace: So as <hi>mercie and truth may meet together,
and righteouſnes and peace kiſſe each other,</hi> Pſal. 85. 10. <hi>The
Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord as rivers of vvater: he
turneth it vvhither ſoever he vvill,</hi> Prov. 21.</p>
            <p>This phraſe, <hi>Rivers of water,</hi> may be here uſed <hi>meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically</hi>
or <hi>litterally.</hi> If <hi>metaphorically,</hi> the <hi>metaphor</hi> may
be taken from Gardiners, or marſh-keepers, who uſe to
let in ſtreams of water into their gardens, orchards, or
medows, when and where they think good: and to let
them out when they will. If <hi>litterally,</hi> the phraſe may
have reference to former acts of Gods turning waters
from their naturall courſe, as it pleaſed him. <hi>For the Lord
cauſed the ſea to go back,</hi> and thereby ſaved the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but
deſtroied the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> Exod. 14. 21, <hi>&amp;c</hi> He made alſo
the waters of <hi>Jordan</hi> to ſtay their courſe, till all <hi>Iſrael</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
over into <hi>Canaan,</hi> Joſh. 3. 16. To theſe evidences of
Gods power over the water hath the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> reference,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 114. 3, 5. where he thus ſaith, <hi>The ſea ſaw it and fled:
Jordan was driven back. What ailed thee, O thou ſea, that
thou fleddeſt? and thou Iordan, that thou waſt driven back?</hi>
The Lord alſo <hi>opened a rock, and the waters guſhed out: they
ran in the dry places like a river,</hi> Pſal. 105. 41. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
in reference hereunto, ſaith, That the <hi>Rock followed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114824:22"/>
them,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 4. by the rock metonymically he mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the waters that flowed out of the rock; and they, by
Gods ordering providence ran along in thoſe places
whither the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> removed their ſeverall ſtations, and
ſo followed them. The Lord alſo upon <hi>Elijah's</hi> ſmiting
the waters of <hi>Iordan, divided them hither and thither.</hi> So
did he again, when <hi>Eliſha</hi> went over <hi>Iordan,</hi> 2 King 2. 8,
14. It is alſo noted, that when the armies of <hi>Iudah, Iſrael</hi>
and <hi>Edom</hi> were in a dry place where was no water, unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly
there came water, and the country was filled
with water, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 20. This was done by the Lord. It
is expreſly ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 33. that <hi>the Lord turneth rivers
into a wilderneſse, and the water ſprings into dry ground.</hi> And
again, <hi>verſ. 35. He turns the wilderneſse into a ſtanding wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and dry grounds into water-ſprings.</hi> All theſe and other
like inſtances evidently demonſtrate, that the Lord hath
ſuch power over rivers of water, as he can turn and order
them, as it pleaſes him. Now waters running in rivers
have a violent courſe. He therefore that can turn them,
can much more turn the hearts of Kings.<note place="margin">Agit omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens in cordibus huminum etiam motum volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis eorum ut per <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at quod per eos agere ipſe voluerit. A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> de gra &amp; lib. Arb c. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> Kings are men:
and <hi>the Almighty acteth in the hearts of men, even he moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of their will, that he may do by them, what he will doe by
them.</hi> To inſtance this in Kings, God turned the heart of
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> to <hi>Abram (Gen.</hi> 12. 19, 20.) of <hi>Abimelech</hi> to <hi>Iſaac
(Gen.</hi> 26. 11.) of another <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to <hi>Ioſeph (Gen.</hi> 41. 39.)
Of <hi>Achiſh</hi> to <hi>David</hi> (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 6.) Of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> to <hi>Elijah</hi>
(2 <hi>King.</hi> 1. 15.) Of <hi>Iehoram</hi> to <hi>Eliſha</hi> (2 <hi>King.</hi> 6. 32, 33.)
Of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to <hi>Ieremiah (Ier.</hi> 39. 11, 12.) to <hi>Daniel</hi>
and his three companions (<hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 48, 49.) Of <hi>Evilmero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dach</hi>
to <hi>Iehojachin</hi> (2 <hi>King</hi> 25. 27.) Of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to the Jews
(<hi>Ezra</hi> 1. 1.) Of <hi>Darius</hi> alſo to them (<hi>Ezra 6. 7, &amp;c.</hi>) Of
<hi>Artaxerxes</hi> to <hi>Ezra (Ezra</hi> 7. 6.) and to <hi>Nehemiah (Nehem.</hi>
2. 8.) Of <hi>Abaſuerus</hi> to <hi>Esther</hi> and <hi>Mordecai (Eſt.</hi> 2. 17. and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114824:23"/>
6. 10.) Of <hi>Agrippa</hi> to <hi>Paul (Act.</hi> 26. 28, 32.) and of many
others. If thus the Lord have the Kings heart in his hand,
much more the hearts of others. Kings, by reaſon of
their ſupreme power, and the dependence of many on
them, uſe to be moſt reſolute and inflexible in their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.
He then that can turn <hi>their</hi> heart, whoſe heart can
he not turn?<note place="margin">Omnium volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates ita ſu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Dei poteſtate, ut eas quo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerit, quando voluerii faciat iaclinari <hi>Aug.</hi> de Gra &amp; lib. Arb c. 20.</note> God ſo hath the wils of all in his own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
as he can make them inclinable whither he will, and
when he will: yea though they be many conſulting and
conſenting together about the ſame thing. For <hi>multitudes
are but as many waters (Rev.</hi> 17. 1, 15.) He that can turn the
one, can turn the other. Though moſt of the Tribes had
held with the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> yet God ſo
wrought upon their hearts, as all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came
to <hi>David,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Behold we are thy bone and thy fleſh, 2 Sa.</hi>
5. 1. And when they had revolted from <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi>
a while after all the people were at ſtrife to bring king
<hi>David</hi> to his throne again. Yea the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> having
alſo revolted from <hi>David,</hi> it is noted, that the heart of all
the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> was bowed even as the heart of one man
unto the King, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 9, 14. There was a Councell of
malicious enemies gathered together againſt the Apoſtles:
but upon the advice of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> they all agreed to let the
Apoſtles go, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 40. Thus we ſee how God can make
Councels and multitudes to yeeld to good advice, though
it be againſt their former principles.</p>
            <p>Were our hearts well diſpoſed to the duty of praier
which we have in hand, and did we perform it in faith and
with fervency, it might be ſaid of our performance, as it
was ſaid of that performance which the <hi>Iews</hi> did in my
text, <hi>So we faſted and beſought our God for this, and he was
intreated of us,</hi> v. 23.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
